[Music]
all right hello and welcome to act imp
livestream number 42.0
it's april 16 2022.
welcome to the actinflab we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
you can find us at the links on this
slide
this is recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide us feedback so
we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams and sid
thanks a ton for joining
really looking forward to this
conversation
if you want to learn more about active
lab activities check out
activeinference.org okay we're here in
active livestream number 42.0 and we are
starting to learn and discuss this paper
robot navigation as hierarchical active
inference
in the journal neural networks october
2021 it's by ozone catal timber bellin
tune van de mali bart dote and adam
saffron and some of whom we're looking
forward to speaking with in the upcoming
weeks
and this video is an introduction for
some of the ideas and just some
background and context and
rapidly assembled fun and memes
that we'll go through so it's just a
introduction of a discussion and we hope
that if you're watching live or later
that you can still
contribute to this and we're going to go
over the
main aims and claims of the paper
then the abstract roadmap and then walk
through some cool keywords in context
which will be great to hear students
perspective from working with robotics
which is an area that certainly i've
never actually been involved in so
going through some of the more applied
work that we're going to see with
robotics and also some of the more
formal aspects from active inference and
then this third vector that maybe we
both share which is some of the
biological basis of navigation so
we're going to just go into the
introductions first
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and all pass to sit so sid
i'll walk through your slides but yes
let's hear it
let's go to slide 9 and before i even
address myself
i would say
that we need to address the elephant in
the room that this is live stream number
42 which is one of my favorite numbers
and uh the favorite number for a lot of
people because it's the answer to life
universe and everything so um this is
the first time that i am
like coming to an active inference live
stream and i'm actively inferring the
whole idea of active inference itself
i'm very new to the field so um so yeah
i'm very excited to learn a lot of
things and yeah just as we are on this
slide right now 42 has a lot of other
references that you can check out um on
that wikipedia link
okay we're moving to the next slide um i
usually document like the many things
that i've been up to um
at this particular link and um in the
next slide i highlight uh like the few
uh places where i have had the fortune
to be at so i
formally have studied computer science
and design and um i've
like meandered um by accident and by
intention in a lot of different places
um that you can see here so i studied
computer science at a university in
india which practices a lot of hands-on
experience and that's where i got my
start in robotics and a lot of other
things then um and then studied
further um and through various
participatory workshops and internships
at space organizations media labs and
then spent two years at financial
services to understand how money works
and was introduced to robotics mostly
through open source software in the
bottom most thing that you see here
that's the google summer of code program
and i would go into more detail about
how that robotic journey even started
these days i'm very much interested in
how coordination happens and how
we can think about
security of um like countries and
communities in general and more
importantly all the emerging aspects of
society that's technology economics
culture and policy so i know that active
inference is a study of autonomous
behavior and we are moving into this era
where decentralized and autonomous
organizations are
like gaining a lot of popularity as well
as like mainstream acceptance uh
increasingly so it's very interesting to
see where this new field of study that's
active inference um that is a field that
is invented in our lifetime like it's
very rare to see that you get to explore
a field that
that is so recent and
has a long history like through
connections to other fields so it's
definitely an evolving area which can
help explore other evolving areas and
that's what i find very fascinating
about applying active inference in the
way that it's applied in this paper as
well so i'll try to explain like the
history of
robotics in a way through the
lens of my experience with it so one of
the first things
that i did when i started studying um so
as you can see i started studying in
2012 and immediately jumped into like
all the robotics labs that i could get
my hands on in university and one of the
first tasks that was
very
appealing to me was like multi-robot
teams like how do teams operate um that
teams have been like a constant
um like fascination for me throughout
life like human teams teams of um
biological organizing um like
organizations and organisms such as ants
and bees and then teams of um like
robots um and we derive a lot of
um like inspiration as well as a lot of
um
like biomimicry um kinds of techniques
in
multi-robot exploration as well so the
specific topic that we were studying is
in the next slide which is multi-robot
terrain exploration so if we go to slide
these were the different um like
techniques we were studying like just
like ants leave pheromone trails and
different signals for
other members of their colony
we tried to model these kinds of
similar techniques like recency like how
recent was it that a robot that was
covering a particular terrain that has
been um that hasn't been explored before
how recently was that covered so you can
imagine this as like a grid so a
two-dimensional grid and you see the
green squares those are the multi-robot
teams so the green square represents a
robot and they are trying to explore and
map out this entire area as a team and
the assumption is that they can
communicate amongst themselves and in
certain cases they cannot so
the red
squares represent obstacles and you will
see a similar obstacle map in this paper
which in which they use a warehouse
but we were using similar
similarly configured different obstacle
maps both in a simulated environment as
well as a physical environment so
we explored different approaches back
then which is
things like just representing them as an
automata like giving them very simple
deterministic rules which they can
follow and those could be imagined as
simply as conveys game of life like the
glider pattern or similar patterns that
you might know and then we moved on to
more animal inspired or bio-inspired
techniques which is
a technique like recency
in which
the robot leaves pheromone trails in
each square and each square has like a
countdown timer how recently was it
visited by any other robot so this can
be understood as ants leaving trails
which decay over time and this gives
other ants an idea of how to
like map that surrounding region
effectively and then there were very
simple approaches which were more suited
for the digital world such as simply
node counting that how many
robots have visited this node before so
every time you visit any square you just
increase its count visit count by one so
that helps the robots in understanding
okay this area has been visited five
times and the surrounding squares have
only been visited two times so i should
maybe explore the unexplored regions
first so these were different techniques
that were used and
we
moved on uh published a few papers and
were also inspired by military
organization techniques the typical ooda
loop or the observe orient decide an act
which is kind of
applied active inference in a way
so
we did
we did explore that like clustering
approaches and different ways of
conquering the whole map so this was an
exploration and exploitation problem
that um that i had like the opportunity
to study in like second and third year
so of my undergraduate computer science
and then i went on to
um like fancier things thanks to the
google summer of code program so this
was a project with the italian mars
society which reports to the european
space agency and here it's it was more
about autonomous navigation working with
a human so this was a robot and a human
team working together
and the next slide shows um
like how it actually happened so if we
go to the next slide and play the video
um we will see that
that it is meant for an astronaut who is
safe in a martian habitat and the robot
is a rover which is
exploring the martian terrain outside in
a more dangerous environment so every
movement of the rover comes from
the astronauts movements which are
mapped from an omnidirectional treadmill
that the astronaut is walking on and
similarly there's feedback received from
the rover's camera which feeds into the
astronauts virtual reality headset so do
note that this was back in 2015 when
headsets were clunky when
things moved very slowly but kinect was
all the rage like mapping body movements
mapping um like um
robot movements in an unexplored
territory using 3d cameras which is uh
which is a technique that this paper
also uses using
rgb and depth cameras um so those were
the techniques which still
are very popularly used even today so
this was my introduction to
understanding how
different
like robot and human teams can work and
how tele-robotics and tele-presence can
work so my responsibility in this
project was to do the entire networking
architecture and ensure that there's no
latency or there's no feedback in which
a robot can enter a dangerous state just
because the astronaut did not receive
the information on time so
this is how we began and the
operating system that we used in that
particular experiment is on slide 16
so whenever the video is done we can
move to the next slide so
in slide 16 you see a husky
robot so these are open source robots
that are very popularly used with the
robot operating system and we'll keep
coming back to this particular
framework of ross so ross became
extremely popular it gains its
reputation from the earliest darpa
challenges in which a very popular car
uh they just crossed through a through
an entire desert terrain navigating
autonomously so ross was an open source
robotics library
which was built out of that and you see
many different
sensors and actuators on this particular
rover so you see a lot of symbols which
will be repeated in this particular
paper paper as well so the task of a
localization technique is to gather all
these sensor inputs fuse all those
inputs so the sensors can be understood
as imu or
like measurement units inertial
measurement units such as like
accelerometers and speed and all those
measurement metrics then you have camera
which is similarly um rgb that's red
green blue
colors of
the visible spectrum
and then you have 3d sensing um in the
in the sense
of the kinect sensor that you see on
that particular robot and you would see
a similar setup in this paper as well
they use a turtle bot to wire robot
which we will which we will get into
which is also using ross and it uses the
same concepts as we used in that
particular paper so all these different
attributes such as gps 3d sensing
odometry camera and imu are
inputs to the robot localization
technique and all of this together is
meant to estimate the three-dimensional
surroundings of a particular robot and
all these techniques do not use active
inference they used probabilistic
methods which we will slightly refer in
the paper so it's very promising to see
um that if we are inspired so much from
biological ways of navigation we
we should rather use a technique which
like organisms have evolved
to be so effective at
like over so many years and as humans
wayfinding was considered a survival
skill for a long long time before we
entered the era of google maps and we
just totally lost like the technique of
finding our way around rural um urban
and natural settings so
wayfinding and navigation and
localization and mapping was a technique
which um is very familiar to anyone in
their 70s or 80s if you ask them
how would you find your way around a
city block or the jungle they will have
their own ways of navigating that so
they will
either use natural cues like wind
direction uh the way the sun is setting
the map that they have already covered
asking people around so these kinds of
techniques
are built in our human brain and it's
very natural for animals to
use that as well in urban as well as
their own natural environments so this
paper goes into these big many big
questions which is in the next slide
slide number 17 so
over to daniel um
where he
illustrates all these wonderful
connections
good thanks for the
innovation on the live stream
format a lot of fascinating background
and
it sets us up really well to discuss
some of the big questions of this paper
and some of the big questions in general
so
one big question
just the kind of thing that would bring
somebody to want to even read this 2021
paper or future work is how do
biological
like evolved and human created
mathematical statistical and robotic so
several different kinds of human created
entities how do biological and human
created entities engage in actionable
tractable adaptive navigation in complex
conditional and changing landscapes and
that's a question that one could ask
about everything from the organismal
level
to the colony level
arguably also an organism but in a
little different way and all manner of
biological systems and then here is a
really nice slide from this bill ant
robotics project where they did a direct
side to side of the harvester ants
anatomy
and also their robots anatomy and that's
kind of like a bridge that takes us into
a different space first with the walking
around the warehouse and does it does it
stay standing when it gets pushed and
can it localize when somebody turns off
the light in the room and these sort of
basic
um though still relatively advanced but
also relatively
basic
tasks and settings
and then off on the right side here
are some of the visions and
representations that people use for when
those low-level activities are such that
if a robot can resist being pushed over
then how does that have complex
feedbacks with society so
it was just something that you also
impressed upon like the very holistic
nature of this area and also just how to
keep a lot
on
the table talking about it so that's
what will be fun to talk about what do
you think
yeah
i think before we enter into the paper
itself i would want to understand from
you like what has been your learning
from
observing and behavior and studying
their
actions in such an environment
like in natural as well as
artificial environments
i can
hopefully accurately relay an anecdote
for my phd advisor professor deborah
gordon
and she would often talk about how there
would be at a conference or some type of
competition and this is something i've
observed but to a lesser smaller extent
is there'll be a presentation of an
algorithm or a robotics implementation
of so-called swarm algorithm or ant
colony algorithm ant colony optimization
we see it on the
pure optimization or computer only but
also a lot of bio-inspired robotics
design
and
one common feature of these algorithms
is that there's some like underlying map
that's shared like when you mentioned
the grid counting of course there has to
be like a mesh network so that the
robots kind of have basically either
telepathy or some kind of common signal
even if it's asynchronous or something
like that but there has to be some sort
of like updating it of the grid in their
mind
and
being in the field and also drawing upon
what we know about what we know about
ants the nest mate when it's deciding to
forage or not it doesn't know how many
seeds the colony has how many seeds are
out there what the right decision would
be so it must use stochastic
interactions that it receives locally
and cognitive constraints to make its
decision
and then once it's out there there's no
telepathy amongst the ants there's no
queen control there's no forager groups
that all like tell each other orders and
all of that so
that navigation is also multi-sensory
and related to their cognitive
constraints but also their finesse in a
certain niche and a harvester ant is not
gonna forge well in the arctic and so
understanding how it's that interplay
between the nest mate and the colony and
the variability of the environment it's
a really rich area and it's easy to
bring in
other
modalities that humans can use like
long-range communication
and understanding how those novel
affordances for decentralized systems
design
do or don't relate to some of the ways
that biological systems work that's a
really fascinating area
yeah
and
the reason i think that this paper is
relevant first of all
because it's um based on active
inference which is uh like the
study of how the human brain would react
in certain scenarios but more broadly
how a biological organ like organism or
an organized colony would react in those
kinds of situations and
just like you said
the map may not be shared in certain
cases um the map
the team might be decentralized
communication might be
unavailable these are extremely
realistic situations even for groups of
robots
today so
now you can imagine these as
robots who are exploring
the fallout of a nuclear
um situation um like when a nuclear
plant needs to undergo maintenance um
and humans cannot enter that area so you
cannot assume 100 communication when the
robot is mapping out that area so
this is one of the important reasons why
some amount of cognition and some amount
of
active inference of the terrain is
extremely important and our
infrastructure in robotics as well as
communication is only now getting there
like with the new standards introduced
in 5g and 6g networks we will start
getting into like scenarios where robots
become parts of our daily lives and they
already have so i'm based in singapore
and it's very common to see cleaner
robots and teams of
like helper robots moving around
like in university campuses as well as
airports and shopping centers so
these
robots
have covered the entire terrain already
so they use um like very basic
approaches of obstacle avoidance and
trying to clean the entire area and
complete their objectives
and
there is very little stochastic
action going on there because most of
those tasks can be completed in a
hard-coded map that is shared among
those um robot teams in a very specific
highly connected environment but when we
start moving into more urban
environments where this cannot be
guaranteed we definitely need approaches
like the one described in this paper so
so yeah with all that context we can
jump into the aims and claims of this
paper
awesome so just to read some of the aims
and claims which we're going to revisit
a bunch the paper is robot navigation as
hierarchical active inference and some
of their main claims were that they are
going to first propose a hierarchical
generative model casting navigation as
minimizing expected variational free
energy so that is what brings all of
these areas of navigation robotics
under the umbrella or drawing an edge to
active inference framework
we show how perception localization
mapping and navigation naturally emerge
from optimizing this hierarchical
generative model under active inference
so that's sort of the theory and
background and some of the formalisms
that we'll go through
then they implement the system in silico
on a real world robot platform
navigating a warehouse environment using
camera sensor input only
and then they also have this third angle
not just the theoretical and the robotic
implementation of that
but the biological and they relate their
work to various findings and hypotheses
in biology about navigation in the
rodent and primate brain
okay
um yeah
do you wanna i mean read that yeah these
are
wonderful claims before we jump into the
claims i was very fascinated by like the
list of authors of the paper so i'll
just zoom into that a bit if that's
visible on the slide
so
so you see that three three of those
authors are um located in belgium and
the
last author really fascinated me because
they come from a center of psychedelic
and consciousness research which happens
to be one of my favorite facilities in
the entire world focusing on these kinds
of topics so
i would also like to ask you that how do
these uh kinds of
like multi-disciplinary research um like
show through in this particular paper so
obviously we have teams of engineers and
researchers from belgium but we also
have an author from a very different
field and how do you think that
contributed in this paper
that'll be something great to ask them
when they visit but i think at the
general level we see
uh several factors including like of
course a shared interest common
framework in active inference
also i'm sure some uh
well to point out in this specific case
but it's a great question and it's an
important question
okay so
um
[Music]
i'll read the abstract first half and
then
or the first three localization and
mapping has long been a standing up
localization and mapping has been a
long-standing area of research both in
neuroscience
to understand how mammals navigate their
environment as well as in robotics to
enable autonomous mobile robots in this
paper we treat navigation as inferring
actions that minimize expected
variational free energy under a
hierarchical generative model we find
that familiar concepts like perception
path integration localization mapping
naturally emerged from this active
inference formulation
moreover we show that this model is
consistent with models of hippocampal
functions and can be implemented in
silico on a real world robot
our experiments illustrate that a robot
equipped with our hierarchical model is
able to generate topologically
consistent maps
and correct navigation behavior is
inferred when a goal location is
provided to the system
yeah i mean that's a lot to get into so
yeah i mean
so the paper makes a very simple claim
like if we broadly look at the paper it
makes a very simple claim that active
inference works and it's able to
consistently reproduce maps which are
representative of the physical world map
so
this also goes into
this literally goes into the map is not
the terrain um kind of discussion that
we have been having in active inference
live streams and
in this case they are able to
consistently reproduce a particular kind
of map that is a warehouse kind of a
setting and they compare it with many
different approaches and
there's many different tasks that you
can see here so the highlighted tasks
tell you that there's perception which
is understanding the entire environment
then
combining all the parts that can be
taken from point a to point b
and then
localization which is understanding your
own position as a robot in that
particular environment
and then mapping as you are doing all of
these things simultaneously localizing
your position and state as well as
mapping um the entire region um while
you're doing that and all of these are
naturally emerging from
like formulating it as um like active
inference which is
minimizing uh expected variational free
energy so um so yeah just before we go
into uh more detail like do you want to
explain to robotics
researchers who might visit this live
stream about why they should
care about variational free energy and
probably these new words that
that might be very important for them
nice thanks for that
very clear summary and definitely we
hope that this kind of a presentation at
least in the dot zero and also in the
group discussions it's like a two-way
street so people are going to have
different amounts of familiarity with
some of the robotics as well as with the
active inference so to anyone who's
anywhere in that space
i think there's a lot to be said for
just taking a first principles approach
that's sort of a simplicity in elegance
route there's value to be found in
transdisciplinary approaches like
localization and mapping
and cognitive affects
and emotion some of the psychological
frameworks that we've been discussing in
other live streams or other papers and
so
there's value in not just simplicity but
in finding connections like complexity
and patterns across systems
and
i think also for something that is
clearly so nascent in its development to
be able to
as sid is describing
have some functional
closure of maps
and cast this problem of like
where is one and how should one act and
what is the bigger space map look like
and all of those things which as
discussed in the real world have all
these other
challenges like the communication of
those maps and everything however just
at the individual wayfinding route
drawing on first principles from biology
and being a part of a conversation
that's clearly already functional but
also has a lot of potential is probably
a good thing to at least listen to
okay so how do they
do that
here's the roadmap
in the beginning they introduced the
problem and some of the background just
like we've done in these last minutes
they then discuss some biological
perspectives on navigation
they then formulate in sections three
and four
the hierarchical active inference model
for navigation it's going to be a two
layer model and we're going to go into
it a lot and there'll be colors that are
consistently associated with the levels
they then discuss the experiments which
is the implementation the mm robot
embodiment of the robot and then they
have some discussion
okay yeah
yeah before we enter into each of these
specific uh topics um like i would share
what i had shared with um daniel a week
ago when we were started um
approaching this paper so
i mean this paper is exceptionally well
written even if you're not from any of
these fields so
just um looking at like the language
that's used it's
very easy to follow for the most part
and they make references to
like topics which
people will be familiar with so they
explain active inference um free energy
and all these different concepts of slam
and very technical terms in an extremely
um simple language which which is why i
think it's a great paper uh to start
with if you are new to either of these
fields robotics or active inference
very true because i know i was
looking up a lot of robot citations
watching videos and learning a lot
because it's just totally not my area
and i can imagine somebody with a
different background would have a
different experience so it's i agree an
awesome written paper and it exists for
anyone who wants to go into more detail
and
check out the citation networks if
you're in the future
uh they listed several keywords active
inference robot navigation
deep learning slam simultaneous
localization and mapping and then
ratslam which is a biologically inspired
version of slam so let's just go to your
active inference meme
if you would like to give a real time
meme reading please feel free to
yeah so the meme explains itself and
this is uh essentially
the teaching robots like um
as if you're teaching a child and i
think that is uh essentially what all
kinds of learning techniques come down
to and there was another meme of uh like
a toddler reading neural networks for
babies which is not in this presentation
but uh that meme essentially
meant that a neural network is learning
how neural networks work um so this meme
is inspired by that that in order to
solve a particular purpose you need to
infer actively which means you need to
firstly be active and that's the first
condition and the second condition is
that you need to be constantly inferring
uh like your own assumptions about the
environment uh about um the observations
that have
uh
transpired in the last few time steps
and then continue to do both these steps
in a loop and in that combination of
those two loops
you are able to solve that purpose so
the meme is inspired from rick and morty
in which the only sole purpose of that
robot is to pass butter uh and in this
case uh
that sole purpose of just uh
implementing active inference in a robot
is all that's needed to solve that
particular
task and that is intended for the claim
of the paper so that is why active
inference as a whole i think is
um like all encompassing when it comes
to
like doing all the steps that we covered
in the last seconds
i'll only comment on what you said
because it's so true that as a holistic
and composable model it'd be possible to
bring in different sensor modalities
different communication
connectivities
different actuator possibilities and
active inference could
grow
in terms of how it's being used so this
is like uh
relative to some other possible
algorithms which would have to be
composed in a bit of an ad hoc or in
principled way this is a way to explore
just that that u infer actively could be
for the
robot
in condition a or the robot in condition
b depending on the generative model and
the markov blanket and the external
states in the world itself in the
context so
um let's just go straight into the meme
analysis of this second video meme you
have prepared
yeah
meme analysis is something new
that might be unique for this live
stream at least in this
animated format and
as you can see in this particular meme
and in the previous beam that a robot
has to forget all their existing slam
techniques that
robots have popularly used so we go into
many different techniques that are cited
in the paper so one of those techniques
is obviously rat slam which we will go
into next but um probabilistic robotics
is like this popular book this classical
book which was used by robots of the
last decade or two and it describes many
different approaches of how slam can be
implemented and all techniques that we
see
in conventional robots today whether
it's
like a robot that's cleaning your house
or a robot that's serving you food in
one of those experimental restaurants
all of them use probabilistic
robotics techniques and
this meme in particular goes into
firstly the mission of this entire
participatory lab which is act infer and
serve and once you do that once you do
all these three things as a robot you're
able to successfully navigate your way
around these
very confusing terrains which might be
complex and
dynamic
and on the top you have a diagram which
describes how deep learning methods
typically work and how this paper
implements one of those techniques with
an active inference flavor on top of it
so
dan do you want to describe uh like
how active inference and deep learning
like how this
like combination of these two
fields has come through in this paper
sure first i'll
uh interpret the meme and then describe
the deep learning but then we'll get
into the more details as we actually
walk through the paper so i see the the
act and first serve of actin flab which
is open to anybody who wants to
participate
and then it's a little bit like the
experiment where people are passing
basketballs to each other and then
something unexpected crosses the screen
and many people will not report seeing
that other thing crossing the screen but
there's a lot of analogies to other
cognitive contexts so it's like we're
focused in the lab but then also we
have to be aware of the unknowns and the
unexpected and the anomalies within the
anomaly space and then that's how we get
to four
which is like
the tetrahedra which is bigger than just
us
anyone so how to be doing that nestmate
thing
that we can juggle and three numbers in
our head at once or seven numbers in our
head at once or can only grab two things
at once or even fewer so how do we
actually use these limitations that we
have and be part of still a bigger
navigation so it's nice meme basically
this paper is going to present a method
that uses some
model structures from active inference
but also uses some
more
mainstream deep learning and machine
learning techniques
and those methods we'll talk about more
like the specifics of how they're
combined but it contains both things
that are like machine learning neural
network type approaches as well as that
being structured in an active inference
way
and that active inference structure when
it's just with simple matrices can be
looked at like in the model stream one
or in active inference a step-by-step
guide that's the very simple matrix
multiplication
very austere kernel of the active
infrastructuring and then here because
some of the data includes like video
data and it's being implemented on
modern hardware it does have like a deep
learning machine learning aspects and
modules to it
okay so here's slam finally finally the
keywords
so
researching it i found this paper are we
ready for service robots
and presenting a data set for slam
and on the bottom right it's showing
some different scenes as well as how
they change
and the paper concludes that with
respect to this challenge of
simultaneous localization and mapping
that various factors can often confuse a
robot and so one can imagine this is
just like an algorithm that has a blind
spot or some sort of area of poor
performance for any number of reasons
and that's exactly how these authors
begin the paper with
being able to robustly explore and
navigate an environment has been a
long-standing challenge in robotics so
the paper just begins with
what we've been talking about which is
that this is like a perennial and a
cross system problem but also in hashtag
2022 it's far from solved in real world
settings
what else would you add
i mean i especially like like the title
of the paper which
describes why we are doing all of this
the title is are we ready for service
robots and in the previous meme we saw
that the third pillar the of the
trifecta after act and infer is so
so all the robots that
that we are building and most of the
applications that we focus on are meant
to serve that they have uh they have
service as an objective function and
that
is what makes this task challenging
because if you are replacing human
actions by a robot um you
have to forget all the assumptions we
make when dealing with like human teams
because human teams are dynamic and they
uh learn on the fly and obviously they
might be as they might not be as
effective as a robot uh who might be
better evolved to uh or better suited uh
through its architecture to consider
depth and different different kinds of
attributes and a changing environment
but
that that group organization poses a lot
of challenges to traditional slam
techniques such as changing even one
thing in that environment can um like
greatly modify uh what map the robot had
made and
you can imagine this as like there's a
map
and you had localized your position with
reference to particular objects in the
map and then you move those objects so
the robots world just shifted all around
it literally and that
that simple change might be very obvious
for humans to detect
but for a robot which is using those
reference points to localize itself in
the world and construct the map out of
it that is a big challenge in
traditional slam
approaches so
so yeah many people who have tried to
train a robot before it cleans their
house by
like driving the robot around in
different rooms
is very familiar with this particular
problem that when you move a chair
in between the robot just completely
forgets its entire sense of its
surroundings so
so yeah
that's why i really like this reference
yeah yes and that's gonna come into play
with the internally maintained
hierarchical generative model that the
robot has on board and that may offer it
some resilience against these kinds of
changes so that's why we're going this
route at all
and one
adjacent work that's discussed in the
paper is rat slam
so i will play the videos that if you
want to maybe describe or contextualize
rat slam
yeah so rat slam was this
bio-inspired technique which
really solved
such slam um in a very simple manner uh
which is that you it it could do perform
uh as effectively as other slam
techniques which relied on um like
expensive equipment and replaced it with
like a simple camera which has in
imperfect information so the video goes
into it in a lot more detail and uh
we'll cover it in the next slide as well
uh but essentially it's a hippocampal
model which means that it
it models
like a rat's brain and is able to
like map the world and localize the
robot that way so i think the video is
very self-explanatory and the next video
will explain it even more about how the
map is constructed so yeah let's look at
that one okay go for it
so what is happening in this second
video
yeah so the second video is one instance
of rad slam which is open rat slam so
this was a code base that was released
both for c plus plus as well as the ros
operating the robot operating system and
here you see um this one particular
robot called the irat robot mapping out
an australian environment which is an
urban environment that you see on the
top right and you see
the robot making specific circles around
certain loops and making
both exploration decisions along the
boundaries as well so this is very
similar to how a rat um or a biological
organism would explore a particular
territory so all of this is being done
with a single camera and that is the
main um like achievement of this
particular piece of work so
through this paper you see that the
inputs
on the top right are mapped into
the images that you see on the bottom
right
and those simple images are what's uh
being used to map out the terrains so to
the human eye that particular input is
extremely blurry and not high fidelity
enough to map out a terrain
effectively but as this paper explores
it can very effectively do that even
when we degrade the image quality by a
lot so that is um that is why rat slam
became very popular as a sighted
reference in this paper because it's one
of those bioinspired techniques which
comes very close to active inference
techniques that this paper goes into
so yeah that's what this video covers
and it explores different kinds of
terrains as you can see
awesome
so the paper
in the introduction
introduces the relevance of this
necessity of the deep navigational
functions that humans and other
organisms have but also that robots we
would want to design having
that's the main theme here
if we learn from biology and bring
action into
robotic slam we may be able to
have a way to approach these questions
and then they say okay well how are we
going to bring action into slam because
this is sort of the inactivist insight
that having the perfect map in one's
head is like the knowing but then the
knowing how to act is not always trivial
even with the most high resolution map
like one could know exactly every
molecule of the car and still not know
how it would fail in an environmental
situation
and that's what an activists and an
activism gets at which is like what if
somebody doesn't have the
digital twin
model of where things are on their body
but actually the representation if there
even is one is more about how the body
should move or how one should act so
that's called the pragmatic turn or the
inactivist term
and in the terms of cognitive science
that's the 4e cognition so even though
that is about the richness of usually
human cognition embedded and cultured
extended etc etc
it's interesting to again see that come
into play with this discussion of
robotics like what if there are cultural
practices around movement in a space how
could that
or be integrated into a robotics model
so there's a lot um that goes with this
taking serious of action selection
as a real primary imperative not just
the hypothetical mapping so
they say well let's use active inference
as a process theory of the brain that
casts action as perception as two sides
of the same coin not sure if it was
action and perception but still maybe it
stands both ways and a process theory is
just like a way that it gets done
so how do organisms get it done or
taking one step removed in the
instrumental direction how will we model
organisms getting it done and then
people can debate about what organisms
actually do but this is like us
actionably mapping that territory
in section two they introduce some
neural correlates of navigation which
we're going to discuss in the next slide
and in section 3 they bring the question
of navigation in terms of active
inference and so that's when they go
from this hierarchical bayesian
generative model of localization
and on one hand connected to the active
inference framework and on the other to
this prior work on machine learning in
robotics
and that was also related to their
previous paper so the others of course
have previous work and there's related
work too
okay
so
uh the h slash e oh do you have anything
others said i mean
yeah in the introduction they raised two
very important points before
they start to go into the actual
techniques they have implemented so they
say that humans um easily explore and
map their surroundings without much
extra thought or considerations like
intuitively we build a logically
consistent map without needing accurate
distance measurements and we find it
natural to think about navigation in
terms of sequences of moves towards
locations and when we are considering
moving to that new location humans
typically do not consider lower level
tasks such as opening doors or lifting
feet
in this paper they go into
like lower level tasks as well because
those kinds of assumptions cannot be
made
for robots and they also mention an
interesting point which is that the
working of the human mapping and
localization hasn't been thoroughly
understood
but
the best models we have so far are
present for rodent navigation which is
where rat slam and other techniques come
come from so
this um like predicates the work that
goes on into this paper and how they
model this as a multi-agent active
inference
task
great
so the h slash e system
is the hippocampal slash enter rhino
system
and homologous brain regions are here
shown for the mouse the rodent the
macaque which is a type of primate and
the human
and these brains are sort of aligned
and shown so that one can see how these
regions are evolutionarily related to
one another
and then on the bottom are some examples
of histology or tissue stainings showing
like kind of a cross section and a
little bit more detail at the cellular
level because as one might imagine this
has been studied and there's many many
copious numbers of like review papers
and so it's like a whole thing
how people have studied this like many
others but
here is a citation that they provided
in the paper i believe
which was a buzaki paper
about memory navigation and the theta
rhythm in the hippocampal and torino
system so suffice to say that the
function of this
coupling of brain regions has been
modeled in some very fascinating and
rich ways
and trying to understand how the same
brain regions
in different functional
ways
can
be
integrating different aspects of
selfness and memory navigation
wayfinding some of the complexities of
how these different functions are
related to each other
anything to add on that and then we'll
look at how that has been addressed in
the active inference framework
yeah
the only thing i would add is one
particular image that i'll paste in this
particular slide which is
like look at the similarity between the
tasks done by the hippocampus and the
intro rhino system and the similar setup
sensors on this particular robot so
we use extremely
similar architectures to center
ourselves in the world which is we use
sensors in the form of sensory organs
and
obviously ears and eyes and all these
are sensors but all of that is computed
in that particular
region of the brain which is considered
the robot localization module in this
particular robot so
so yeah that's what that analogy i find
interesting
awesome and that's with the action
states in the sense states like just
like the sensors and actuators we could
have two of the same kind or 50 of the
same kind or 50 different kinds and
that's like the kind of multi-sensor
fusion that's also interesting to think
about
and
they write in the paper we will ground
the following discussion of the
hippocampal enter rhino system in terms
of its role in generalized search and
navigation and the citation here is to
this kaplan and frist and paper we're
not going to go over this model right
now but people could pause look at the
graphical model go to the citation and
we'll hear about it more from the
authors how did they build on prior work
all
i'll add here unless i said if you want
to ask them who's totally chill would be
um
they use a bayesian graphical framework
and we're going to see a lot of bayesian
graphical frameworks
the nodes the circles represent
statistical variables
of different kinds
and then the edges reflect the sparsity
of influence of connections amongst
those variables so like two variables
that influence each other have arrows
pointing between each other and this is
a bayesian graph way that is sometimes
used to represent models graphically
that's kind of playing on graphical in
two senses like it's visual it's
graphical like a picture but also it's a
graph like a network so it's something
that is a representation of models at
the intersection of those two senses of
graphical and we use them a lot in
active inference and in this paper they
made active inference models for
navigation and search and they overlaid
it on some of the plausible neural
anatomy of the brain and some of the
functions that those regions of the
brain have been modeled or seen as
performing
great
okay yeah
the
uh
paper also on the biological section
explores the grid cells and we saw the
grid cells also in rat slam
the grid cells are in the enter rhino
cortex so it's in the he system
and they represent a largely triangular
or hexagonal tiling of space organized
according to egocentric reference frames
now it's hexagonal in the flat plane but
what shape is it in higher dimensions
and they write that the regularity of
these repeating grids provides a basis
for path integration via estimating
distances and location in terms of the
direction and frequency with which this
metric grid metric tiling is traversed
and
this was pretty interesting to hear how
they framed it in physical domains it
has been observed that the spacing of
grading representations varies as a
function of the space being tiled each
is smaller
and more fine-grained if an agent is
situated within an enclosure or larger
and more coarse grained if it is
situated in an open space
the granularity of tilings appears to be
influenced by brain stem locomotor
nuclei potentially reflecting an
inductive bias for greater speed being
more likely in larger spaces
as well as by
exteroceptive stimulus such as optic
flow
so it makes me think about driving at 70
miles per hour and it's like
one still has this extended sense
of mobility and well i could make a left
turn over that space and time scale and
that's as natural feeling to somebody
who's familiar with driving in a certain
context as like i'm running at this
speed and i can make a certain turn at a
certain speed and then the optic flow
reminds me of a great experiment with
honeybees where they had them forage but
they had to go in and out through this
long section where there was an
alternating stripe pattern and so when
the stripes were thick like let's just
say a meter of dark and then a meter of
light then they would forage a certain
distance and they would be able to do
the waggle dance and communicate it to
their nest mates but then when that was
replaced with a very fast alternating
stripes it increased what's known as
optic flow which is just the simple rate
of change like the frame differencing
across the retina and the b's were
foraging a shorter distance
because it was like
their estimates of optic flow were
higher and i think that speaks to also a
point that stephen has raised in the
chat which is the information geometry
versus information geography
and that could be connected to a lot of
different other areas so that's just
something to think about with how's the
actual space represented how's the
perceptual space represented and the
grid cells are something that people
have modeled as
being at the intersection there from a
cognitive perspective and from a tissue
perspective
anything to add
yeah so
yeah stephen has raised a great point
above the geography and i think in
humans and organisms
like ants and bees it's more about
survival and that is why they um
like attach a different kind of a grid
sizing for different kinds of terrains
and yeah your description of driving in
an open wide road is extremely accurate
and so is the bees one and i think it
comes down to minimizing
error or
like being more specific um in
constrained environments um so
so if their actions um are as
wide and as
um
like
broad ranging as
an open environment that might uh
like be harmful for their objective
function which is not only
like reaching from point a to point b in
that
small environment but also like survival
like just banging into
an obstacle if they are not being very
specific about their grid size so
so i think yeah it comes down to optical
optic flow as well as um i think these
survival functions which are like hidden
states um in like the models of all
these agents
awesome
um
they
move from the biological
towards the formal
by
writing speculatively
if hippocampal pattern completion is
inherently predictive or generative in a
bayesian framework
then this could help to scaffold the
development of more sophisticated
predictive abilities for the rest of the
brain so i think this is a very deep
area that'll be fun to explore in the
conversations but it's almost like you
can bootstrap more complexity off of
something that is already providing
a more complex and oscillating signal
so i think the richness of self and the
placed basedness
and learnability there is quite
interesting to explore
and they also
uh note that there's ample evidence that
spatial awareness is at the core of the
mammal brain with explicit
representation for pose heading in
location
so what
i wanted to explore here in the
discussions was
location is the core of the mammal brain
or cognitive functions in general or in
insects too or something no it's
olfaction no it's emotion no it's this
so where do some of these core
functions fit
and then they close the section by just
writing
uh
taking it from the introduction with the
robotics to the biological in section
two and then they say in the remainder
of this paper we will further build on
these insights using a process theory of
the brain deeply rooted in predictive
processing active inference so you'll
note that other than our additional
context like we haven't gotten into
active in the paper but that's when they
cross the rubicon and from here on out
we're going to be talking about the
active inference formalization
anything else to acid
yeah
i mean i really like how you framed
that particular importance that um
different kinds of organisms and
like robots have to be assigned
when when we are dealing with
like their objective functions which is
is location um
like the most important state for them
or
um are other senses more important and
if we are thinking about like
self-driving cars and uh like evidently
like tesla is very particular on not
using lidar and
like laser depth sensing technologies it
it's trying to just use rgb depth
cameras and trying to navigate
the world and i think the same is true
for
comma which is
another open source self-driving toolkit
so these kinds of toolkits that exist
for navigation in the physical world
they
just rely on location and
like vision as their only source of
input and not other senses
so
so yeah it's interesting how you can
modify the importance of these different
attributes to achieve different tasks
all right
so into section three
navigation as hierarchical active
inference okay so this is where
active inference gets applied in the
theory level and then it gets applied in
another way when it becomes simulated
and then in another way when it becomes
enacted etcetera so we cast the slam
problem in terms of a hierarchical
bayesian generative model
the agent reasons on two different
nested levels
so there's going to be the use of a
higher and lower to describe these two
different ones but one could use
different spatial metaphors like inner
or outer or
however else on a higher level but this
is going to be consistent with the
coloring and which one is placed above
or below
on a higher level for long-term
navigation and on a lower level for
short-term perception
on the higher level the agent is capable
of reasoning in terms of sequences of
location it wants to visit i want to go
to the post office and then to the
university and then back home
without having to worry about the
intricacies of how to control its
actuators to get there like i'm not
overthinking the footsteps and how to
cross the street
on the lower level the agent can reason
and plan in terms of observation
sequences without needing to think too
far ahead
short term action selection plans based
upon ongoing
input
we will distinguish between the higher
level and the lower level actuation by
calling them moves m and actions a for
the two higher and lower levels
and the sensor readings like the visual
input but other sensors could be added
to at the lower level are called
observations and that's modeled with an
o
and that reminded me of the relationship
between strategy and tactics in chess
whereas
in strategy there are more heuristics
like control the center or
the knight on the rim is grim because it
has reduced mobility that doesn't
actually suggest
how to do it or what kind of a direct or
oblique strategy would actually be
realized in which way it's just sort of
like general ideas and then there's the
tactical and the rollout and all of that
in the in the specifics of the situation
which cannot be really thought too far
in advance because even just two or
three in advance the branching is so
complex
that
it's not really useful all the time
although some brute force approaches
have used that to great success and it
may work in certain cases but it's not a
general strategy just to roll out
tactics further and further and then
hope that strategy just falls out of
rollouts of tactics so
i'm sure you'll have some thought on
that but how do you think that frames
this as a multi-scale statistical
problem and then it's going to be
approached from this bayesian active
inference way
yeah i think it perfectly models it so
you added strategy and tactics i would
only add objective objectives um like as
the third element to that so objectives
strategy and tactics are like these
different levels of tasks that people
want to achieve and this is not only
true for uh the tasks that uh that you
refer to like chess or um other
applications but also like when we go
about in our own life like our
higher level task can not just be going
to the post office but
achieving some objective as a result of
that which is
i i'm going to the post office because i
might have received an admission letter
from uh from a university and that has a
higher level task on top of it which is
uh this has broader implications to my
career or life in general so one
person's or one robot strategy can be
another robot's tactics it's and the way
you define moves and actions is totally
arbitrary and dependent on like how
reliable your sensors are so
i think
the levels are
the place where we draw the line between
lower higher or inner and outer levels
are
dependent on the sensors which is the
ground truth that we can reliably
measure in that particular movement
the only thing i'll add there is that
also just like you said where one robot
strategies and others tactics this
nesting of bayesian generative models
can be
three layers it can be four layers etc
so there's arbitrary design of these
graphs and we've seen like in
metacognitive papers like active
livestream number 25 on metacognition as
mental action it actually is like action
and perception all the way up all the
way down so just because a layer isn't
modeled we have an interface for the
unknown through
the blankets that we do specify
okay
so let's look at it specifically all
right on the left is figure one it is
the prototypical generative model of an
active inference agent as we discussed a
little before the nodes in the graphical
model represent random variables
where the gray color is indicating the
observed variables so the observations
are observed
in gray
and then the actions are also observed
so one could complicate this assumption
but we're assuming that like if the
robot is hitting the gas that it knows
that it's actually doing that motion
an observation at the current time step
o sub t is generated by the hidden state
s so it has the white node so it is a
not directly observed but it's like a
parameter in a model
the generative model of the robot
which in turn is generated by the
previous hidden state and action at time
steps t minus one so it's like here's s
in the past and it's marching forward
and then it's influenced by its prior
states as well as by how actions
influence states if at all
and future states and observations
depend on future actions which are
determined or not completely determined
but that's but have a statistical
relationship with the policy pi
and policy pi
is
sequences of actions if one has a policy
depth of one then the action at the next
time step in the policy are the same
inference but when we have a horizon of
planning that's deeper than one
it means that policies are actually
sequences of action and that's part of
the complexity of cybernetics and so on
and on the right i have a little bit cut
this generative model into a grid so the
now time step is the action that we took
in the past
the hidden state inference at that time
unobserved and the real time observation
and then
the
left to right is the past
time step the now time step the next
time step and then just deep future time
steps whatever the horizon of planning
is
and this is a discrete time model
there's also continuous time active
active inference models and they can be
used together but it's not in this paper
and at the top is policy selection and
there's a lot of cognitive apparatus
that might connect to this pie but
that's also not modeled here
action selection is these a's
and those are just your actions through
time i moved e2 e4 and then nf3
and then the hidden states are whatever
the hidden states are that are being
tracked as being influenced or related
to policy selections via action and then
hidden states embed observations and
that's what makes it a partially
observed markov process and then because
it's a
[Music]
policy variable that's being modeled
here it's a partially observed markov
decision process because it's not just
the markup process inference it's also
having action as a parameter that's
planning as inference
anything to add on
one yeah i think adding the grid really
helps
simplify the different steps that
the agent has to
take and how it's composable with
different policies that might connect
from different objectives so
so yeah the observed and
unobserved are i think the more
important key pieces here which is uh
which again can be
have like which can have different
probabilities because um
as you go
through deeper layers
you can consider the previous layers
observation um previous layers
unobserved state to be your current
layer's observed state so it depends on
how much
like probability you assign to
like the strength of that particular
observation and
yeah
one last thing which is the observations
in the future are unobserved so just to
note that there's a difference between
the past and the future and one could
also imagine that maybe there's a
forgetting or something like that but
that's a very key difference is that the
same type of variable like actions are
unobserved in the future we can't say
well we'll make these three moves it's
like but what if another chess piece
blocks that specific move well that
would be dumb of them to do but would it
so that's part of the complexity of
strategy so
figure two is where they go from this
single layer model this is kind of the
kernel of the model
and they're going to
introduce a slightly more complicated
graphical model this is going to
specifically cast navigation as a
hierarchical generative model for active
inference and so the lower level is this
again more tactical more local visual
perception on the bottom
filled in observations that's the
real-time camera data
coming in
is one way to think about it but another
way to think about it is actually by
looking at the arrow direction it's
being generated
using some underlying states
and then the actions at that lower level
are also being observed in the past
and at the lower level highlight in blue
the model is entertaining beliefs about
hidden states s
that agents and the agents pose p so
here's the s and the p like each time
step there's a hidden state
and the pose
the hidden states are giving rise to the
observations o
and then the hidden state and pose are
influenced by the previous state
that's the arrow coming horizontally
pose
and action or the higher level model in
the case of the initial states and so
here is like at each
time step so here we're like in this
blue block with a t
um
[Music]
like at the faster model
time step
and then at the slower level there's an
injection
from this like slower click that shoots
something in and then that in influences
the rest of this blue block
and then it's carried forward and
there's another injection like a slower
time scale at that more strategic
level
and at the higher level highlighted red
the agent reasons about locations
the next location is determined by
executing the move on m so here's the
more slower updating movements like
where one is in that map and then this
is the
more fine-grained action selection
what what do you see in this figure
yeah so um
yeah it uh like it's a continuation of
the previous uh figure and um like the
speed differences are what's interesting
here like uh the higher level being just
a two-step process whereas the lower
figure has more involved actions
involved
so
so yeah you see that observations exist
in both these layers but
there's more
depth of unobserved states in that
particular lower layer
i hope that now by
filling in some formalisms related to
this
that we can put a little detail because
there's a lot that could be said about
this and i hope that we've been at least
consistent in our descriptions but we'll
look forward to
hearing from the authors on it so
um
[Music]
they write in active inference the agent
will infer beliefs over these hidden
states based upon experience
looking back into the past observations
those are the observations from the past
that the computer has access to as well
as infer future actions through a
process of minimizing variational free
energy this is where they're going to
introduce this free energy minimization
as kind of like a model metric that
helps do
parameter selection parameter
optimization on this type of graph so we
have some graphical structure believe it
or not and it could look different that
does strategy and tactics it's like the
skeleton but then the real challenge is
to have the video data come in and to
have the movement data actually modeled
and to make that happen on limited
hardware and so on
and so what they do is first describe
that in terms of equations and then
they're going to talk a little bit later
about like how the equations get adapted
into using neural networks and actual
cameras and sensors but this is just
going to be still at the equation level
going from this graphical intuition
about how to do strategy and tactics and
how to have them modify each other into
an analytical um way of framing it
so
p
is the joint model of
o s a pi that's the observations the
video camera data that states
hidden states at this
layer
and the actions
and the policy
different aspects of the past present
and future are modeled as sparsely
connected so one could believe it or not
that those are sparsely connected so
called in reality but in this model
there's actually quite sparse
connectivity amongst variables even
though if
um if it's new to you it might look like
a circuit board or something but
relationship to the all versus all that
it could be connected
this is a quite sparse connectivity like
this bottom left one doesn't influence
this top right one for example so
factorization is a way that that
sparsity of the variables can be
converted into a factorized equation so
we have this joint distribution which is
like the ultimate panopticon
distribution but because their sparsity
of connectivity different parts of the
model can be like partitioned out
differently so it's like this big joint
model that gets separated into separate
parts and each of those one can
interpret as being like the distribution
of that
so like there's the distribution of
policies the district over two policies
or over continuous policies then there's
the distribution of action states that
are taken depending on the policy so
like given that i intended to move a and
then b
did i actually take a
then there's the state underlying
distribution in green hidden state so
that's not directly observed the blue is
the distribution of observations
conditioned on hidden states that's like
a bayesian hidden markov model and then
there's this relatively more complex and
combinatoric term that is asking well
how do states
depend on past states and actions
and then how do actions actually depend
on policy decisions
and how do the observations in the
future depend on the hidden states in
the future
so it's taking this joint model and
breaking it down into a few different
pieces that as we'll see can be
simplified
and that makes this problem tractable in
a way that just the all by all
non-factorized non-factorizable model is
much more difficult to fit
yeah okay absolutely and yeah this this
goes into like the practical
um implementation of how such a thing
can be done and the interesting uh
factor in this formula for me is like
the combinatoric term which takes in the
previous states and um like multiplies
it with the current state um and
like this is one of
the ways active inference can be modeled
and i think in previous live streams uh
like there might be different
implementations of the same framework
where os a and pi are used in many
different um like formulae and
arrangements
great point yes
though there are some differences in
notation across papers
there is hopefully um more coherence
than not so knowing this framework helps
one understand active inference domain
different domain models okay
so
how is free energy going to be used to
fit this model
both on the sort of perception as
inference side so that's the part of the
model on the bottom that's more like a
what is my pose given the visual input
and what action should i take in the
short term
and this deeper more navigational
layer
at in the red how are those going to be
reconciled and parameterized which
includes action selection and policy
selection how's that going to be
parameterized using a single criterion
so they use the variational free energy
and it's calculated up to the current
step t so variational free energy
as contrasted which we'll get to with
expected free energy variational free
energy is like the parts that are
observable are easier to calculate over
one can imagine so that's the
variational free energy and the expected
free energy is going to have continuity
with the variational free energy but
it's going to introduce this
complexity of calculating expected free
energies about unobserved observations
and actions but they're similar but it
goes like from first variational free
energy is looking back and that's the
more perceptual component and then
there's a deeper expected component once
a time horizon is considered
so
we can go into this more with the
authors but briefly in the first line f
this variational free energy is being
defined as the expectation that's the
fancy e
of the difference
between
the q distribution which is the
variational distribution that's under
the control of the experimenter of the
robot and that's like a simplified
distribution family so just like fitting
a linear model can be done even if the
data are super non-linear and you're
totally misled fitting a linear model
can be quite fast or fitting just a
parabolic model can be quite fast so if
you constrain what model family you're
willing to use for q
though there are still some quite
expressive families that are also
tractable then you can try to minimize
the expectation of the difference
between the distribution that you're
controlling and this distribution that
you'd like to know that's going to help
you go a long way towards doing policy
selection
this expectation can be rewritten using
a kl divergence
and that can also be rephrased as a
difference between
a kl divergence and another expectation
we can go more into this with authors
and i think that will be great to hear
their explanation but for now just want
to leave it at that level of detail
yeah i agree and
i mean the broader point that i
see from this particular framing is
like representing it in terms of
divergence and evidence and this is how
not only they use it for their
experimental setting but this is how the
actual free energy model will be
implemented in a real life situation as
well in which uh the first term which is
in their control um may not be um like
in their control when the robot is in a
dynamic environment
like that so
in this particular paper in a warehouse
environment this kind of a framing makes
perfect sense um but
when the setting might be different the
framing might also need to reflect that
nice and and also there's that
complexity minus accuracy interpretation
yeah
okay so
here's where they move from the
variational free energy f to the
expected free energy g so they write
crucially in active inference the agent
will not only optimize its generative
model by minimizing f for past
observations in addition the agent will
also select actions that it believes
will minimize its future surprise
however future observations are not yet
available the free energy f cannot be
computed and the expected free energy g
is used instead to compare the effect of
various policies or actions in relation
to the goal of reaching the preferred
state so wouldn't it be simple if we
could just infer how the map looked in
the past and then make decisions based
upon how the map looked in the past but
that opens up to all these
basically failures of function in
changing environments
g in formalism 3
is a
sum across over a given time horizon t
so the expected free energy g of pi and
t policy and time
for a given certain policy pi and time
step t in the future is defined as
and this is going to be another set of
formalisms but we can just pull back
and remind ourselves of that sentence
from the introduction active inference
is a process theory of the brain
that casts action as perception as two
sides of the same coin
so
variational free energy which is more
perceptual like
because it's looking in past observed
states
and then g which is going to introduce
the uncertainty of action in an
uncertain future
how an f how are f and g similar or
different
how are they being cast as two sides of
the same coin
how through the present
are those two processes being reconciled
because time step five from now is going
to be like now
then
so how will we have continuity in
dealing with certain moments like now
but then there's things that we're
uncertain about in the past and the
present and the future and they're all
very quite different kinds and they have
different relationships to past actions
and that's like the blockchain angle you
can't change the past you can change
your interpretation of the past but then
there's a different kind of variability
or openness in inferences about the
future so
these are great questions to learn about
and think about how are f and g similar
and different what is variational free
energy what is expected free energy what
is free energy of the expected future
which baron millage at all have
introduced and what other kinds of
representations
of this nexus
are relevant to think about because
these
cited papers and shown equations do not
exhaust the richness of that setting
but
it's awesome how they pulled back to
just this
it's a function g
of what you do
pi
and what horizon you're considering it
over
tau
and then implicitly how you think about
all of that and how you think about that
so they both pulled out to a level that
i think will provide a lot more
discussion but also we have to get
specific in order for that robot to be
in the warehouse
yeah and
the only fascinating observation for me
um
like obviously there's a there's a lot
uh in this slide because
uh this is the entire model this is the
crux of uh the entire calculation where
you have
variational free energy and
the expected free energy and you see the
similarity between both um these
formulae where divergence and log
evidence is mentioned and then
complexity and accuracy are terms of
that formula and eventually it comes
down to risk and ambiguity in the
expected free energy
formula when
all the probabilities are given a
certain policy and on a particular time
horizon um so which is represented by
tao so these terms like divergence
complexity risk
are like in one bucket um
and
log evidence accuracy and ambiguity are
like in the
same similar category in those two
formulae
awesome um i think we will as we expect
the unexpected will start to actually
accelerate through because the goal of
the dot zero is really to set a lot of
that context because that is what brings
one to the trailhead so to speak for a
lot of the details that they're going to
present and of course the accuracy of
their experiments and the implications
and everything like that
so we're just going to sort of
continue on knowing that that
getting there is getting quite a far
away with this paper and then we're
gonna go slightly faster through many
other aspects of the paper just like
give it a first pass
so um here in formalism five
they are casting p of pi the
distribution of policies as a soft max
sigma
of the free energy on policy and this
temperature parameter gamma
this is casting planning as an inference
problem which allows one to go from like
the relative free energies of different
policies to a decision on those policies
and when there's high temperature it's
like the pie chart is made but one is
still
um just picking from the different
policies um as if they had relatively
more equal pies whereas when the
temperature is low like absolute zero
then one is selecting the best policy
like more than it should be expected in
a way
um
and so that gamma reflects the
confidence that the agent has in current
beliefs over policies so when there's a
lot of confidence then the most uh
the best expected policy selected always
when there's low confidence then it's
not taken into account as much and
that's of course a fun to think about in
the context of like expecting the
unexpected i think i can i think i can
and then it says on the bottom right no
one had the heart to tell him he was
going the wrong way so one can think
they can and be acting consistent with
their model
and going the wrong way relative to what
so there's a lot again there that
connects like the math to some broader
questions that we all have
what do you think
yeah totally agree and the meme really
brings the point home
so
yeah let's go to the next one and um in
live stream number 37 people can read
about this dual interpretation
of
preferences and expectations and about
how they co-realize each other
so section 3.2 they move to the
hierarchical generative model for
navigation
and here it's the same
higher and lower model with blue at the
lower time scale red at the higher level
and it's going to be basically as we
spent more time on previously but just
applied to this multi-scale navigation
problem where it was being approached a
little bit more abstractly before so in
formalism 6 they're going to have their
big joint model
be
all the things that one would want to
know in this whole nested model
that's why previously when we saw the
p distribution there was only four
variables because it was considered at
like just a more simple
kernel layer and this is writing it out
for the whole
nested model where there's actions and
moves so it moves across these two
layers being jointly considered
and then it's going to be like this
multiplication between the lower level
distribution and the higher level
distribution
because it can be factorized across
these two levels because they're
sparsely connected
because of how it was designed
so that simplification takes like sort
of an all by all model
and just
at this level that corresponds
graphically to the sparse connectivity
allows those two to kind of twist
a little bit independently from each
other
yet also
containing a common basis in this joint
distribution
anything to add
no i think this will be clarified
further in the next slide which goes
into global policy selection
all right so in the higher level uh red
the global policy is emitted every move
is treated independent of each other
this hierarchical arrangement allows the
system to reason about its environment
further ahead both temporally and
spatially
and so then they take this joint
distribution
and it gets broken down into these three
terms from formalism 7 we can see the
generative model decomposes into terms
for both the lower level dynamics blue
i.e how actions influence the next state
and pose
so we we broke the blue out from the red
and then there's this other term which
we can talk about from the joint
distribution
what do you think
yeah
yeah i think the
this is uh where it comes to expressing
in terms of g which was the expected
free energy and we see those terms
repeat here and i think this is i think
the most important formula of this paper
in which the global policy selection
happens
and at the higher level yeah
okay so
as we saw before with the simpler
version first there was a decomposition
on p there's a factorization on a p
distribution we saw this with like with
a simpler p
here
they then got turned into an f and a g
here we have a more full featured p
it is also going to be
turned into an f
which is the variational free energy and
then a g
so this is f of the hierarchical model
they write now that we've fully
specified our generative model that was
p the factorized joint distribution
we again turn the variational
f and then later the expected g
free energy that will be minimized in
active inference
so it's a variational uh distribution q
that they're fitting and they take the
same approach as they took earlier with
the single layer model and they reach
this hierarchical free energy
that can be rewritten by the bottom row
as the decomposition of the free energy
of the lower model and of the higher
model so i think it'll be great to hear
the authors like how did they reach this
and what
do they think it means and
so on but i think the awesome question
to think about here is how do we think
about free energy minimization in
multi-agent and multi-scale systems
how do free energy decompositions work
and what if
nine do really well then one doesn't how
does that
group outcome
get traded off against well everybody's
doing a little bit worse but isn't that
better than one person doing a lot worse
well it depends by how much you mean by
a lot and a little in the situation and
so on so how does all of that going to
be amenable to these kinds of seemingly
cut and dry
decompositions
yeah that is an excellent question and
another question that i would add to
this is
how many terms can you decompose this
into as you think about more and more
models so here here we have a lower
level and a higher level but
can there be multiple levels for
different kinds of scenarios
awesome
okay
so
they are now going to pick up on that
bottom line there's a low and high
decomposition of the hierarchical
variational free energy and they write
this falls apart into a term for the
lower level and the higher level of the
hierarchy which we can further unpack
for the higher level we get
and then they provide a expansion of
that f high and f low
and these have the same complexity and
accuracy interpretation as we saw with
the previous f
except that this complexity minus
accuracy can be understood as being
about only the higher level and this
complexity minus accuracy
on lower level can be interpreted as
being about only the lower level so it's
like been a separation of consideration
between these levels but again they're
coming from a common joint distribution
so that is just like a example of taking
the analogous logic
and path that was followed on the single
level model
then
using this composable framework making
the nest degenerative model and then
being able to apply the same kinds of
techniques to reach the same kinds of
conclusions but now in this different
context
anything yeah totally agree yeah
splitting it into like these very
specific terms and differentiating the
forest from the trees where high is the
forest and the lower level are the trees
is
very very
helpful and it also shows how they are
related and not related
awesome um so now they're going to make
that f to g move when considering future
time steps tau the variational free
energy becomes an expected free energy
which again unfolds to a term for each
level in the hierarchy so they're going
to do that f high and f low
type decomposition but it's going to be
about g the expected free energy and so
here's the low on the right and the high
on the left
and so here there's that same risk plus
ambiguity
but now it's being applied to the
decomposition between the high and the
low
and so similarly to equation four this
unpacks in a risk term to reach a prior
goal location
and an ambiguity term intuitively this
means the agent selects a route to its
goal location with the lowest ambiguity
hence if the agent operates in a
completely static environment without
uncertainty this basically becomes
equivalent to shortest path planning so
that was really interesting to you know
hear about again in the context of what
you described like well-mapped
well-connected real-time updating
highly controlled settings the future is
more like f than it is like g
because it's like you can just trust in
the future that you'll get a snapshot
update and you'll be able to make the
perfect move
because you'll be able to do shortest
path planning and traditional
optimization techniques because you'll
have no ambiguity um about
the
future basically in the short term and
then that gets more complex when there
actually is
different kinds and different patterns
of ambiguity in the future so it's just
like such a cool way to hear about it
now
yeah good enough said it better
similar thoughts on this particular
framing
okay so that was section three
in section four
there now we still haven't seen
active
applied yet we haven't seen any action
perception loops it's been like very
analytical to this point
so now in section four they're going to
actually bring that
generative model
into active inference so they write now
we've established our generative model
in the variational free energy
optimization objectives we present how
to instantiate such a model in silica
for navigation on a real robot with
camera input so it's kind of interesting
because in silico often means like we
only simulated it but here it means we
implemented it on a silicon processor
yeah in a uh
in a real embedded situation and so
um
the observations are the raw pixels from
the camera sensor and the actions
consist of the commands specifying the
linear and angular velocity so that is
just taking that generative model
structure that we described kind of
abstractly like the we just talked about
the observed observations but is that a
one pixel camera is it a 4k video is it
lidar like this is where they are going
to connect it to the specifics of what
they actually do in the robot
yeah yeah the only thing will add is
again this picture because
it's such a helpful picture in framing
the
pixels and the sensors that that are
being captured in their case as well so
they are taking just this camera inputs
which is rg and b values
for this particular paper as well as
like the imu units and the odometry
units which is velocity
awesome
so in section four one
they
highlight the visual perceptive aspects
of their model we're not going to
describe it here we'll hear about it
soon but for one focuses on that visual
perceptive aspect
for two
which we're also not going to focus on
here
takes it a little bit
out from the visual perception you know
how is the tree recognized given the
retina and this is like the path
integration
around those trees
so this is a path integration
approach
and then they also
bring up some points about how this has
some similarities on the biological side
and also they introduced this
topological map component of the higher
generative higher level generative model
the red model um do anything to add
especially maybe about that topological
basis of the higher model
yeah so
i mean this is where it's uh attaching
it to like the physical world uh this is
where the lower levels and higher levels
get connected
through these particular formulations so
yeah this is a question i will have for
the authors as well like how is this uh
can cn network represented and why did
they choose this particular
framing of
connecting the two levels yeah they
write the posterior distribution that's
the one that we control is represented
by a continuous attractor network a can
a 3d cube that wraps around the edges
with these different dimensions
so that might enforce some type of
closure
on the network which we also saw
happening with the rat slam but that'll
be a good thing to ask
okay
so then in section 4-3 they highlight
the
the localization and mapping
these are being simultaneously inferred
so it's a slam
and this is um
[Music]
the localization and mapping features
which are another level kind of above or
different than just path integration
and they relate that to the higher level
model
so they provide some other formalisms
and uh
maybe this gets at what we were
discussing
due to odometry integration drift so
inaccuracy about how many footsteps you
took like that's the kind of the reason
why people apparently walk in a circle
when they're lost in a list landscape
because they have like a little bit of a
different step length and so they have
drift in their heading
matching experiences will not have
exactly the same associated pose
these displacement errors are
distributed throughout the graph by use
of graph relaxation shifting the stored
pose according to
equation 16.
this enforces the map to be
topologically consistent even after loop
closures which is often challenging in
metric slam systems so that definitely
gets at stephen's information geography
or information geometry versus
information topology because if we
enforce a rigid geometry then tiny
differences might drive us wild but if
we enforce topological closure then
even if a road like became thirty
percent longer we'd still be able to
navigate from
city one to city two and it wouldn't be
so bothersome
yeah
yeah and
including drift is like one of the
fundamental things all robotics
experiments have to do because um
everything that we formulate via math
never seems to work out well in actual
physical sensors and actuators there's
always that drift term that needs to be
added and i like how they have handled
uh like the drift here
awesome in section four four
they
discuss and highlight the navigation
features and here we'll talk more i just
want to raise these questions because
they make up like three of the
perspectives that are really getting
integrated and recombined here and you
spoke to it right there how do
mathematical entities navigate
like bayesian graph models and
generative models how do biological
entities navigate and how do robotic
entities navigate and
what are their similarities and
differences and different opportunities
and challenges and how will we
generalize and make the right kinds of
connections across different systems
within these domains and across and
among these domains so that's an awesome
complexity question i hope a lot of
people can enter into these questions
and like provide their thought and be
involved in this
yeah i mean this could be a whole
section on navigating navigation which
is um like an interesting topic for
complexity
awesome
okay section five and this will be i
think just fascinating to hear their
hands-on experience about these
experiments which we're not going to go
into too much detail in but in section 5
they describe their setup and
implementation so
this is a tele operation of a mobile
robot in a lab with a warehouse style
and they describe some details about
like what kind of robot they use what
kind of camera was used and how many
data points existed and then they talk a
little bit about their implementation of
how that generative model
became
basically implemented using machine
learning as a lstm network
yeah this is where this is this is the
most fun part of the paper for many
robotics
like researchers because this is like
the standard robotic toolkit that's used
in almost all robotics labs around the
world turtlebot has become like this
raspberry pi of robots in which every
lab has one and anyone can replicate
this kind of an experiment easily and
it's interesting that they have access
to like all these sensors that they talk
about such as lidar and millimeter wave
radar but they only use uh like the
minimal set of sensors they need which
is the rgb data and
that is what they use to collect data
points and they are sampling it at like
an interval which is very close to human
perception like 100 milliseconds it gets
close to
like biological level perception um like
the frame rate that we have for our
sensory organs so
that is
very interesting and the implementation
is even
um more interesting where they
which we have to definitely ask um the
authors about how they use this setup
thank you great
uh in figure three
they show on the right side uh a picture
of the bot turtle bot so there it is
and then on the left side we see some
still images of the lab
warehouse seen at different points so
like here point one on the map is
corresponding to what was seen as like
approaching this wall and kind of doing
a u-turn and um so this is the path that
was taken as it was kind of uh
circulating these warehouse house um
shelves basically um yeah well and also
i really appreciate how you like you
described um the the commonality of
these techniques um because those i i
just didn't know that this was such a
common
hardware and it'd be awesome to see like
what it will look like when people start
to deploy it in different settings
yeah um and it's important because they
use ross first of all turtlebot uses the
robot operating system and um like if
this is the first time people are
looking at a turtlebot and by just
looking at the image you can tell that
it's a roomba with like a shelf on top
of it with many different sensors so
honestly that's all there is so the
movement
movement is done by like the vacuum
cleaner on the bottom
the cleaning robot module on the bottom
of the robot and then the rest of the
rack the rack is full of sensors where
you see the cameras attached so earlier
there used to be connect cameras
attached and you can attach any sorts of
additional
units on top of it and then there's a
processing unit there which
like takes in all those inputs and does
all the calculations on board so so yeah
reproducibility in robotics research is
extremely rare and using a technique
like this uh definitely helps for other
labs to reproduce these kinds of results
yeah thanks for that and i'd be really
curious to learn more also about like
the edge computing
implications like is that a mini pc what
exactly is needed here what if the model
were 100 times simpler what if it were a
hundred times more complex
so in figure five
section five three they discussed their
results and they asked three research
questions
and those are addressed in the following
sections so they ask does that lower
level model learn accurate
representations for inference and
prediction by minimizing free energy so
does the lower level work
two can these representations be used in
the hierarchical model
for generating topological maps of the
environment because although we kind of
didn't discuss it in detail that is that
topological closure that's impressed
upon at the higher level but not at the
lower level so can the lower level work
and then can it be used as a useful
interface with this totally different in
type
topologically closed higher level model
and then the holistic question is
does the system infer sensible moves and
actions by minimizing expected free
energy to engage in navigation like okay
given that the two components are
interfacing does the whole thing do
free energy minimization in a way that
ends up doing so-called sensible moves
that is maybe what um
a person would do if they said just
patrol that warehouse just walk around
without any too specific of a goal but
just make sure that you walk everywhere
pretty much
that's pretty sensible they didn't spend
any time over here
they didn't just go up and down one
shelf so that's sensible even though
there's not quite a heuristic for that
but i think that's really a fascinating
question what is sensible behavior
yeah
and i think they go into how they
quantify sensible behavior by comparing
it with other approaches in the results
so it will be interesting to ask the
authors about that
yeah
okay table one just goes into some
details about their neural network
parameterization we'll hear about it
from the authors so how did neural
networks come into play what was the
process of fitting that
okay
figure four
all right figure four
is the
sequences of the ground truth
observations first row so that's the
video data coming in on the top that's
like just looks like regular video data
reconstructed observations second row
that's the generative model of visual
input and that's kind of like thinking
about this in terms like a course
grading but this brings the visual input
into the robot's terms
corresponding to latent space samples
third row
so this is like potentially um an
internal representation like a layer of
a neural network
and so um
it's just showing that these perhaps
very similar or different scenes can be
differentiated
via
their position in like a higher
dimensional latent space or it's lower
dimensional in the video but it's higher
dimensional than just like the x and the
y
the robot is turning towards the left in
the sequence as can be seen from both
the sequence of observation as well as
the shift towards higher theta values in
the pose cube and that's the pose cube
activation on the bottom row
so this is what it looks like at that
lower model to go from video data
to hidden state estimation the kind of
core screening generative model of the
video
to this latent state internal
representation
to the pose estimation that's going to
come into play at the higher level of
the model they're kind of overlaying
time steps as columns during this
execution of a turn
and showing how different layers of that
lower model are updating
yeah um and i think this is a time
series like you described left to right
indicates um like
10 seconds for example 10 seconds of a
turn of a robot and
that was an interesting comment on the
higher level dimension for a robot is
lower level fidelity for us with those
pixels so
so yeah the way we represent things and
the way it's represented in a robot um
can have very different terminologies
yeah and higher lower inner outer more
less
it's always in relationship and so those
can sometimes get swept under the rug
it's a high dimensional representation
that we did of this
you know what's what do you have to ask
in 42.0 how high
it's just a few pixels
in figure five um they show
uh the generated experience map left and
a comparison map extracted from
localization with our tab map so i show
citation here but i would love to hear
your interpretation of what do they mean
by the experience map is topological
while the r tab map is metric what are
being shown differently here here
yeah so um so yeah they are comparing
the figure that they obtained on the
left with uh the data obtained from a
similar technique so the way these
robotics experiments work is they use
different localization techniques and
they are using our tab
map which is another technique on the
right and yeah the second point is very
interesting and i think that is
stephen's question as well which is
how is the information
geography represented so
the experience map which is uh on the
left it briefly describes how
like the environment is
topologically
yeah closed and
the rtap map is accurate to like
physical world metric
uh units which is measurements so
so topology just means like how
everything is oriented it doesn't need
to be physically precise um as a real
world it's
like wisdom versus
knowledge so topology is more
uh more of an idea that uh that if you
follow this kind of a map you will find
your way and you won't get lost whereas
metric is um like precise
mapping of the physical environment and
mapping it to scale like one is to 20 or
one is 200 whatever that scale may be
i really like that knowledge and wisdom
and then here's um why there's always
the minimum of two and why we respect
both because the topological maps may be
totally non-comparable
in their geometry for two different
entities mapping the same space
and so
if we are both trying to get the
geometry of the geography that's where
it's possible to have the most objective
agreement
on the knowledge
side
allegorically
here
and then the topological side can be so
much simpler
and so much more personalized and local
and can actually help in those way
finding the changing situations
and maybe there's analogy or there's
resonance or there's small
isomorphisms with different wisdoms
but
one has gone down that path and has
basically given up making the image on
the right that other people will just
see and recognize as oh yeah that
totally lines up with what i see
so that's quite a nice point
yeah
okay figure six uh is some more outputs
of the model
so they uh
right imaginary policies
uh oh imaginary policies oh so there's
several images of different things
happening
there's the current state
which is the video input at that time
step
and then there's imagined short-term
goals i want it to look like this i want
the frame differencing
at that time step to be super small i
want to be really unsurprised about
looking like this at that short time
step in this turn you can kind of see
that
piece on the left that's getting brought
more into view as i turn my head left i
don't want to be surprised i want it to
feel normal
and then in the long term goal there's a
lot more like blurriness
because it's not super important whether
the handle is here or here
because it's just an uncertain future
and so these are imagined policies that
can be considered at past present and
future time steps and that's kind of
what the partial observability of the
hidden markov model structure or motif
brings into this picture this is why
it's good to have a generative model
rather than just
a recognition or an input a signal
processing model that's like where the
whole generative bayesian concept and
predictive processing from the
biological side come into play
and also in the future it trails off
these are the same time series and
further and further in the future it
gets blurrier and blurrier until it's
like i just want to be in a horizontal
plane
in the future
basically standing yeah
yeah yeah figure d is like um very
interesting in this particular picture
where they have three different policies
and you see very different results
as a result of those policies
so this is uh like robotics 101 behavior
where you program the robot to always go
left always go right or always go
straight and you
start with these particular policies and
then um understand that these simple
changes in behavior have like such
vast differences in the results
so yeah the sentence you just
highlighted is yeah so so here the three
policies are basically
um
the two different turns are going
straight and so they say when
calculating g low and evaluating the
distribution on policies this results in
a probability close to one to take the
policy go left like look at how on the
bottom row that's the go left policy
it stays sharp in the future
but then
this the policies that diverge
increasingly from the goals at different
time scales
with respect to those goals it becomes
really unclear so it's like i want a
hundred dollars so i'm saving one dollar
per day then at day 71 i expect 71
dollars wow it's exactly 71 dollars
that's like this bottom time one and
this is like i'm losing money every day
i'm getting less and less clear on how
it's going to end up at 100 at this
future time step so
maybe that's not a good policy not
because my expected value is dropping
but because it's just it's unclear how
i'm going to get to 100. and that's
something that can be neutrally said
without even taking a judgment on the
amount at any given time step
yeah
yeah i think that analogy really drives
the point home that you need to choose
your policies according to the goals and
i think all those goals were part of
their uh formulation of the expected
free energy so
i think it's important to ask this to
the authors like how were these goals as
well as policies chosen
and can this be generalized for
different kinds of environments
awesome so figure seven they write um
different goals for the long term path
of figure five so just here's the figure
five again with the
topological closure of the higher model
the lower level dynamics model will take
the corresponding states
as preferred state goals sequentially
so this is where we see that the
connections between the models becoming
enacted so let's just say that um one is
coming around this edge and there's two
options they can continue straight or
they can go right or they can go in
reverse but we're considering forward
motion only so there's two alternate
policy it's not the infinite space
decision making that humans are
sometimes confronted with but here it's
a robotics motion decision about
continuing straight ostensibly to
explore this final right most uh
shelf sequence or taking the right turn
now so go straight or turn right
now what would sensible behavior be if
one had recently or repeatedly visited
the closer shelf then to be more
exploratory it would make sense to like
go straight so that this last shelf
could be explored so that's the kind of
decision that we would want that robot
to be able to incorporate when it's able
to
be making that decision
and so that could be thought of as
having a long-term goal
to be
expecting oneself to be on the far right
shelf here the bottom one
and then in the moment
which one of these actions turn right or
go straight
is going to be preferred
with respect to how one acts now and so
then that's what it means to say the
lower level dynamics model will take the
corresponding states from the higher
long-term path as the preferred state
goals so then one could be like well i
prefer to see myself just right here
already one has chosen a branch
but that is helping you reduce your
uncertainty about being found here later
so that although i really look forward
to also hearing everyone else's like
unpacking of like what is the robot
doing or thinking in that pivot moment
um that's like kind of how i read the
way that the long term planning goals
become imposed upon the lower level
action selections
yep i agree okay
um
what did you see or want to talk about
with the contrast with other slam
approaches
let me see
so yeah this
paragraph um like describes different
slam approaches and um you see the same
like group of authors mentioned from
probabilistic robotics where sebastian
thrun and the co-authors are mentioned
and those were engineered approaches
which uh also used different kinds of
bayesian
like
like statistics and then there were more
bio-inspired approaches such as the rat
slam group which is the 2013
paper and then
um yeah they rely on post can and this
experience map which they compare it
with and
recently like deep learning has
obviously been used on visual slam like
you see in this uh like the bottom
um like bottom of this paragraph and
yeah
the underlined
section is important do you want to
cover that the active inference
allow for a holistic treatment
i think that's where they bring it home
which is they say well yeah yes people
have used this recognition variational
autoencoder model and yes there's been
this topological approach to rat slam
navigation closer and
etc but then
those are often again composed in in an
ad hoc way
uh and so
active inference is providing a possible
way to uh approach it in a more
principled and more integrative first
principles way
okay
um
conclusion let's uh hear it from the
authors people can draw their own
conclusions but i'll just highlight the
last
sentence that we think this research
direction might offer new insights both
on how navigation works in the mammal
brain
as well as how to scale active inference
to real world applications so it's like
those were the three vectors we brought
in with the biological mathematical and
the robotics and then from that nexus
it's kind of like it feeds back out
because now from the brain they might be
learning about the math and the robots
and then the others
in a similar fashion
yeah
yeah and
as the authors conclude the paper they
also bring up some
open questions such as can these
techniques be used for lifelong learning
which is a relatively new field of
machine learning in which states change
all the time and you do not need to
retrain your model but you you do not
you just need to um like retrain
specific parts of your model to
continuously learn throughout the
lifetime of that application so um so
they
suggest something like a sleep cycle but
that means that whenever the
robot is charging that is when it can
update its model of the entire
environment and share that and
do that
active inference approach to achieve
lifelong learning so i'll be
very interested in knowing this from the
authors like what are the weaknesses in
this approach and how can this be solved
to scale for real world applications
awesome and how about just describe what
this last video is showing
yeah so this video is just for people
who are coming from the active inference
lab but want to see like a robot
actually move we have been talking about
robots moving so if we play the video
it's just an introduction to turtlebot
and how people use it in an experimental
setting so
so yeah
the first
few seconds of the video will describe
all there is
awesome um well
we leave a blank slide for the
discussion
sections this was um an awesome and
memorable discussion and it's just the
opening of the 42 when we'll continue on
in a participatory group setting in the
coming two weeks and hopefully have
any of the authors join anyone else who
would like to join in
uh i'll let you give a penultimate
thought but just really appreciate the
the care that you brought to these
slides into this stream
yeah and thanks to stephen and everyone
else who asked questions
yeah okay so if you have anything else
you want to add otherwise we can just uh
thank the listeners and head out
yeah i mean this was my first active
inference
appearance
in
in the sequence of hopefully a lot of
appearances in the future and this
clarified a lot of concepts for me as
well and connected it to one of the
fields that i was very intimately
connected with uh almost a decade back
so
so yeah happy to see connections being
reforged and
yeah looking forward to meet with the
authors
okay
thanks a lot sid thanks everybody and
see you next week bye
thank you
you